## Vikash Kumar

# Institute for Global Health and Development Queen Margaret University

Email: Vkumar@gmu.ac.uk/vikashbsw@gmail.com

## 1. 1. Professional Summary:

A experienced global health professional with 6 years experiences research and development projects on maternal and child health, health system strengthening through capacity building in India. A focus and interest in maternal and child health, non-communicable disease and elderly care. Currently studying integrated non-communicable disease program in India.

#### 2. Education

Ph.D., Queen Margaret University

Thesis Title: Health System Integration in Non-Communicable Diseases in India: An Institutional Ethnography

Supervisors: Dr. Karina Kielmann and Dr. Anuj Kapilashrami

Relevant Course attended: Health System, International Public Health, Global Health and Social Policy, Qualitative Research, Project Management and Proposal Writing.

MA (Social Work), Tata Institute Social Sciences, Mumbai, 2011.

Major: Health and Development

Dissertation Title: Health Care Accessibility in Flood Affected Area: A Case Study of Darbhanga District, Bihar.

Relevant Courses attended: Health and Development, Community Health, Social Science and Health, Health Research, Qualitative and Quantitative Research Methods, Public Policy and Governances

Bachelor in Social Work, Indira Gandhi National Open University, 2009.

Major: Social Work

## 3. Experiences

## **Research Experiences**

Research Assistant, Institute for Global Health and Development, Queen Margaret University, Edinburgh, Feb 2017 – Jun 2017.

- Documenting evidence for the case study for Research Excellence Framework (REF) 2021
- Developed a documentation system to gather evidence from various source to prepare the impact case study.

Research Consultant, Public Health Foundation of India, Delhi, India Apr 2011 – Dec 2011.

Coordinated with Department of Health and Family Welfare, U.P. and partner

- organization for two maternal and child health research projects.
- Literature review and secondary data collection related to cost of maternal and child health intervention
- Recruitment and training of field investigators for primary data collection
- Supervised the data collection process and organised knowledge dissemination workshops

Monitoring and Evaluation Officer, Project Concern International, Patna, India, Mar 2012 – Oct 2014.

- Contributed in developing monitoring and evaluation framework for community mobilization project funded by Bill and Melinda Gates Foundation.
   specialist in program evaluation in relation to project objectives.
- Provided technical support to research project to knowledge management team.
- Analysed family health data to evaluate the health intervention and measured the health outcome in the targeted population.
- Managed data quality assurance system and employed data verification and validation technique to ensure data quality.
- Prepared progress report and dashboard for senior management for Parivartan (community health) project.

## **Social Work Experiences**

Professional Advisor – Research, Social Care Alba, Edinburgh Jan 2015 – Nov 2016.

- Managed care improvement project under supervision of care coordinator and care manager
- Worked as team member to investigate challenges in care delivery

Social Worker (Part-Time), Medha, Patna, India, Jan 2012 – Mar 2014.

- Case Work with homeless and vulnerable adults
- Managed assessment, counselling and social services for vulnerable adults
- Writing grant application
- Coordinating with social service agencies and health care professionals

Area Coordinator, Project Concern International, Darbhanga, Bihar, 2008-2009.

- Working with vulnerable children and families in flood affected area
- Managed flood rehabilitation project and the implemented of USAID/OFDA funded project in Bihar
- Managed documentation and reporting for USAID/OFDA at field level
- Coordinated with local administration and authorities, Panchayati raj institutions, community-based organization and opinion leaders on disaster management strategies

Community Worker, Span International, Gaya, Bihar, 2005 – 2008.

- Managed the community awareness program on water and sanitation in rural areas.
- Formed community based groups such as youth groups, self-help groups for the microfinance program.

## 4. Teaching Experience

Guest Lecture to Social Work Students at Patna Study Center, Indira Gandhi National Open University. India Mar 2012- June 2014.

Courses taught: 1. Introduction to Social Work 2. Social Work Intervention with Individuals and Groups 3. Social Work Intervention with communities and Institutions 4. Social Work Practicum I & II.

#### **Doctoral Mentoring**

 Assisting doctoral and Professional doctorate student in managing research project, literature review, data analysis.

## 4a. Trainings offered

Qualitative Data Analysis Software (NVivo 11) Workshop, Center for Social Equity and Inclusion, India, Mar 2017

Academic Writing, Center for Social Equity and Inclusion, India, Mar 2017

Writing Retreat Workshop, Center for Development Practice and Research, Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Patna, Jul 2016.

## 5. Training/Workshop/Courses Attended

Short Course in Facilitating Learning and Teaching (in Higher Education), Queen Margaret University. (25 Aug – 1 Sep 2015)

Research Grant Application Writing Workshop, University and College Union, UK, 17 Feb 2017.

Intellectual Property - The Value Within, Intellectual Property Right Office, UK, April 2017

Training course on "Statistical & Demographic Data Analysis for Health Personal", National Institute of Health & Family Welfare, India, Nov 2012

#### 6. Research Skills

#### Research Skills

- Project management, proposal writing and preparing grant applications
- Leading and supervising team of field investigator for large scale survey projects
- Literature search using literature database, Literature Review and Systematic review
- Qualitative data analysis (thematic analysis, text analysis, content analysis etc.)
- Quantitative data analysis (descriptive and inferential statistics), large scale data collection, household survey, key informants interviews

## Computer Skills:

- Applications: Microsoft Office Suite, Internet Explorer,
- Data analysis software: Nvivo 11, Atlas ti 7.0, SPSS 20.
- Content development: Video production for online courses, Infographics

## Other skills

- Knowledge of research methodologies (qualitative, quantitative and mixed)
- Data management, data cleaning, data verification,
- Writing for publication and oral presentation
- Web designing, blogging

## 7. Voluntary and Administrative Experience

Co-Chair, Doctoral Student Association, Queen Margaret University (June 2015- May 2016).

Committee Member, QMU Malawi Student Society, Queen Margaret University (2016 - Present)

Board Member, Span International, Patna, India (2017 – Present)

Co-founder, Research Journal Company (2017 – Present)

Advisor, Medha, a charitable organization, India. (2014 – Present)

Co-founder, Initiative, Patna, India (2006 – Present)

## 8. Professional Memberships

Member, Health System Research Cluster, Institute for Global Health and Development, Queen Margaret University, (2016 – Present)

#### 9. Licensures and Certifications

Qualified National Eligibility Test (UGC-NET) for Lecture and Assistant Professor (Social Work), University Grant Commission, India. 2012

#### 10. Publications

Kumar, V. (In progress) Drug Procurement System in Integrated program: A case study of NCD program in Bihar.

Kumar, V. Kapilashrami, A (In progress) Factors affecting integrated service delivery: Experiences of leprosy elimination program in India.

Jayasundara, D., Ahmed, R., Wanasinghe-Paqual, M., Kausalya, T., Das Gupta, P., & Kumar, V. (in progress). Toward better reproductive decision making and reproductive health of Indian

women: The role of relative capability. Gender and Development.

Jayasundara, D., Ahmed, R. Wanasinghe-Paqual, M., De Silva, R., Kausalya, T., & Kumar, V. (in progress) Infant Mortality in Developing Countries, Journal of Human Development and Capability

Singh, AK, Kumar, V. (In Press) A case study of Maternal Death Review in Bhagalpur district Bihar.

Kumar, V., Cheng, S. Y. C., & Singh, A. K. (2016). Impact of flood on rural population and strategies for mitigation: A case study of Darbhanga district, Bihar state, India. *Contemporary Rural Social Work, 8*(1), 45-56.

Cheng, C. S., & Kumar, V. (2012) Pattern of Exploitation and Organized Crime: Study on Homeless Beggars in Patna, Bihar. *International Journal of Scientific and Research Publication*. 11 (2).

Kumar. V., (2011). Health Care Accessibility In Flood Affected Area: A case study of Biraul Block of Darbhanga District Bihar, *Master Dissertation, Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai* 

## **Unpublished Report**

Kumar, V, Singh, H, Saheb, B., Bobade, A. Sawaikar, V., Jariwala, H. (2010) Socio – Economical Study of tribe in Thane District, Maharastra, Report, IRHDP, Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai.

Kumar, V, Singh, H, Saheb, B., Bobade, A. Sawaikar, V. Jariwala, H (2010), Child Feeding Practice of Acute Malnourished Tribal Children – A study in Aghai Panchayat, Shahpur taluka, Thane District, Maharashtra, Study Report, Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai.

Kumar, V, Singh, H,. Sawaikar, V. (2010), Identification of people with disability & Need Assessment for their rehabilitation- A study in Aghai PHC region, Shahpur Taluka, Thane District, Maharashtra; Study Report, Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai.

#### 11. Selected Presentations Given

Kumar. V., (9 Jul 2017), Paper Presentation on "Ruling the Organization Of Service Delivery: An Institutional Ethnography of Integrated NCD Program in India" at 20th Biennial International Symposium of International Consortium for Social Development, Zagreb, Croatia.

Kumar. V., (27 Apr 2017), Paper Presentation on Doing Institutional Ethnography: A Methodological Reflection, Doctoral Student Conference 2017, Queen Margaret University.

Kumar. V., Cheng, S. Y. C, (23-25March 2012) Paper Presentation on Challenges and Strategies of Justice Delivery for Victims of Organised Crimes: Case Studies on Homeless Beggars in Patna District, Bihar" at 35th All India Criminology Conference at Tata Institute of Social Sciences, Mumbai.

Kumar. V., (Feb 2012), Paper Presentation on "Impact of Globalization on Ultra Poor" at National Seminar on Globalization & Women" Mahatama Gandhi Kashi Vidyapeeth, Varanasi, Uttar Pradesh.

Kumar. V., Sinha M, Kumari, P. (April 2011) Poster Presentation on Decentralised Geographical Health Planning at Organised by AmeriCares India at Tata Memorial Hospital, Mumbai, Maharashtra.

## 12. Grants and Scholarship

Entrepreneur Grant, £1000 (June 2017), Developing a Research Management and Knowledge Exchange Web Application, Enterprise Campus, UK,

Research Grant for Medha, local NGO, £1000, Socio-Economic Study of Homeless beggar Population in Patna, Sponsored by Department of Social Welfare, Govt. of Bihar,

Post Graduate Scholarship, £350 (Dec 2011), Tata Institute of Social Sciences, INR 29,800 (Jul 2010)

Field Work Grant, £5000 (Apr 2015) Santander Research Scholarship, Queen Margaret University

Mobility Grant, £1000 (Jan 2015), Santander Research Mobility Grant, Queen Margaret University

Saltire Scholarship for Doctoral Study, £2000 (Aug 2014), Queen Margaret University

QMU International Student Scholarship, £3000 (Aug 2014), Queen Margaret University Scholarship, Queen Margaret University